<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>the decision blog - Kayla Lewis</title><link>https://calculensis.github.io/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>About</title><link>https://calculensis.github.io/about.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=right src="images/me-summer-2022.jpg" width="150" height="150" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello, I'm Kayla Lewis, a professor in the New York City area who loves using and thinking about decision intelligence, that is, those parts of data science, the behavioral sciences, and managerial science that are most relevant to decision making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herein I write especially about how we can use simple math models, systems thinking, and machine learning to improve the quality of our decisions.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Kayla Lewis</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:calculensis.github.io,2022-07-17:/about.html</guid><category>about</category></item><item><title>simple tools, part 1</title><link>https://calculensis.github.io/simple%20tools.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=right src="images/linear.jpg" width="200" height="160" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems like there are two extreme intuitions that are commonly held about how best to go about decision making: The first is to say "The hell with models - I can do just fine by myself!" and the second is "Sure I can use some help, and the more sophisticated the better! And by sophisticated, I mean AI." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these ideas reject using simple pencil-and-paper models, to their detriment! I'll explain why for each in turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the first idea - that we do just fine by ourselves - there are many factors mitigating against this notion, but in the interest of space I'll focus on just one: the recency effect. This effect is our tendency to give whatever we were thinking about most recently a greater weight than other factors that we want to influence our decision. So, for example, to decide where we want to go for vacation, suppose we care about affordability and location. If the last thing we were considering is location, then affordability likely won't get as much weight as it deserves when we are making our final decision. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, if we are taking a multi-lens approach - that is, looking at the decision from many different perspectives - then we run the risk of giving the last lens we looked through more power than it deserves. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can overcome these problems by using simple pencil-and-paper math models, which will maintain the proper weights because those weights will be contained in the relevant equations for each model we consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important consideration is that decisions often seem to involve a lot of variables, and to get anywhere it helps to try and boil these dimensions down to just a few things that matter the most; making a model forces us to go through that process. It's true that AI can also help us simplify things this way...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...which brings us to the second of the extreme intuitions: That the only thing that will do better than we do is something computationally sophisticated like machine learning (a type of AI). For many decisions we don't have time to collect months worth of data (or spend time trying to find and clean data that may already be out there somewhere) and run analytics on it. In fact, for many decisions we don't even start out knowing what data would be relevant or what questions we would want to ask of that data!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A middle approach is to do something that improves on our native mental abilities but that doesn't involve computation - in other words, pencil-and-paper modeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next few posts I'll share some of these models with you!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Kayla Lewis</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:calculensis.github.io,2022-07-17:/simple tools.html</guid><category>basics</category><category>basics</category><category>simple tools</category></item><item><title>decisions and the search-inference framework</title><link>https://calculensis.github.io/decisions%20and%20the%20search-inference%20framework.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=right src="images/choosing.jpg" width="200" height="200" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone, welcome to my first blog entry!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog will be about all things related to effective decision making. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to start with simpler approaches or models that don't take very much time and build up to the more sophisticated ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common theme will be that looking at a decision through as many lenses as possible, given our time constraints, is extremely useful; in this first post I want to explain why that is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making decisions is a kind of thinking, and one of my favorite models describing how thinking works is the search-inference framework. As applied to decision making, it says that thinking has three stages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) We generate a space of possible actions or vantage points&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2) By using the evidence currently available to us, and in light of our goals, we evaluate the strength of each possibility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(3) We choose, or infer, the strongest possibility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common mistakes in thinking can be traced to failing at step (1) or (2). For step (1), the common failure is not generating a rich enough space of possibilities; for step (2), it's not weighing the evidence for each possibility fairly. I'll talk about this second way of failing in later posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Viewing a decision through multiple lenses or models is a way of lowering the probability that we fail at step (1): Each model gives us a different way of viewing the decision we want to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very often, different models will tell us to take different courses of action. It might seem like this is a problem, but in reality it's a strength. Instead of hoping that all models will give the same answer, what we'll do is try to understand &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; the different approaches give the answers that they do; in so doing, it will usually become clearer which choice we ultimately want to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can think of asking models what they "think" just as you would ask your friends what they think. Your friends might give conflicting answers, and that's a good thing! You are definitely expanding the space of possibilities to consider when that happens.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Kayla Lewis</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:calculensis.github.io,2022-07-11:/decisions and the search-inference framework.html</guid><category>basics</category><category>basics</category><category>search-inference</category></item></channel></rss>